[SPEAKER_00]: I want to ask you for advice on how to lead a secular Buddhist group.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are coming to our group expecting meditation to relax them.
[SPEAKER_00]: We don't read suttas or think about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: New people who are coming most probably are not keeping precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what should we do so that people can benefit from correct Buddhist practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just answer it yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Read the suttas and teach them to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you might as well not call it the Theravāda Buddhist group.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I agree.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is a big conviction that people don't want to read suttas because it's boring for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, then basically they would go to another group.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they come to learn about the Buddhist teaching, you present them the Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they don't like it, that's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like... your goal is not to try and keep as many people as possible interested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your goal is to show to those they want to follow it, what to follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and what to do with this expectation that meditation is some kind of relaxation technique?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as I said, like people, everybody that starts, they don't really, they can't tell the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everybody will have their own expectations as putujanas that they come from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: What you do is, you provide them the right information.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if they don't like it, they can find something else that suits their preferences more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you'll be surprised how, despite of how wrong their expectation might be, if people were to hear the right thing, many of them would recognize that they want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they come with an expectation, but you provide them with the actual teachings, so the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: The precepts, the training in those things that we often talk about, and those that see the value in that, they will stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those that don't, will find something else that would cater to their needs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I have a theory that everyone deep inside knows what is the truth, but we just choose to not see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't make them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they don't want to practice the Buddha's teaching once they find out what it is, that's up to them and that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the worst is to actually misrepresent the Buddha's teaching because you think people might not like it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's always somebody who's not going to like something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to run a group, your duty is to present it as clearly as possible what the Buddha was teaching, what the requirements are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if that puts everybody away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you recommend some suttas for starters?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think just you could just go generally just go through Majjhima Nikāya suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: They kind of have a certain, like, balance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they're not too short, they're not too long, and they always, obviously, revolve around the important points.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just any, pretty much, engagement with the suttas can sort of point people in the right direction, so at least they'll know, okay, you know, I can do this on my own as well, I can read this, I can study this, I can try and understand what these texts kind of require from you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're interested in following the Buddha's teaching, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Should we advise them to do some contemplation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for example, ask yourself, are you suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, all of that, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, kind of, a certain, like, a guided type of questioning, reflections and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Your job is to present them with what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might see that, oh, half of these people here come because they think the Buddha was teaching something completely different.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, therefore, I won't tell them what the Buddha was... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You tell them, and if that makes them leave, they leave.
[SPEAKER_01]: New people will come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and I guess, well, we are not gonna, eh, just remove the meditation, because it's, it's used, use it so, it is used so often, and people expect expectations... Yeah, you don't have to remove the period of sitting quietly, but you certainly remove the wrong instructions of meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That are simply not found in the suttas and come with the commentaries and contemporary kind of Theravāda watering down and perversion of the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just, yeah, go through a sutta, do some questioning, some basic kind of reflection on certain themes that are from the suttas, encourage people to think about it, and then tell them, sit quietly now with those reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's assume I am a new person who comes to your secular Buddhist group.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have an expectation that I want to just relax, to feel better.
[SPEAKER_00]: I came here to relax.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you tell them you came to the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is not a relaxation center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go to a spa center if you want to relax.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this place, we learn what the Buddha was teaching, which is suffering and freedom from it, which is not going to be a relaxing truth for most people when they first hear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have no duty or obligation to cater to the expectations of people when they come for the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Supposedly, at least.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you told me this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I decided still not to leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's next?
[SPEAKER_00]: I am...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to relax because I am suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to truly relax from your suffering is to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to start study the suttas, training the precepts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Until you relax on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want a quick fix, you came to a wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, and often I got question, we got question, when some new people come, where is Buddhism a religion?
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends how you look at it, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's certainly today is a religion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you look at the Buddhism as the way it was spread through various Asian countries, it is their religion, it's on the level of their belief, on the level of their superstition, just like how Christianity is in Europe for most people.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the practicing aspect of Buddhism, or the practicing aspect of any religion, it's not really religion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Religion is basically, when it becomes kind of a part of identity and belief of people, they don't really practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're satisfied with that external, just as I said, identifier.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of its customs, rules, rituals and stuff, yeah, of course, it's very religious, like everything else that has reached that level of institution.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is the dhamma religion?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even a philosophy for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a specific recipe for a certain type of behavior, certain types of reflections, that can bring certain type of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's very specific.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people ask, like, how long will it take to make some progress, visible progress, in dhamma, what should I answer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends how long do they make a good quality effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same, somebody goes to become a carpenter, hasn't even started yet, but wants to know how long it will take me to become a master expert.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do it rightly from the start, it will take you very little time.
[SPEAKER_01]: If not, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's what's important to that person, how long will it take me to reach that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then it should be equally important to them to start doing it rightly from the beginning and not delay the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and what should I tell people?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, we are advising people to watch your videos, but some people are saying, like, you are too harsh in speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you are not positive enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't have this image of a smiley monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and they are... it is too much for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it might be too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to work your way up to be able to understand the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, like those, you know, there are those instances in the suttas when that man went to the Buddha and said that his son died or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, he was saying how children are the greatest happiness and the greatest wealth and the greatest benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, no, children are the greatest suffering, the source of the biggest suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he disagreed, he dismissed, he said something, and then went to these random gamblers and drunkards to ask them the same question, because he knew they will agree with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if people are not willing to question their own preferences,
[SPEAKER_01]: of what the practice is, while at the same time knowing that they don't know what the practice is, but still use their own preferences as a criteria of, oh, I like this, I don't like that, then there is no dhamma for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they're all... they're not able to even begin thinking rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody expects the dhamma to be a smiley, laughing monk, just talking about happiness and positive thoughts, I mean, there's nothing wrong to expect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you meet somebody that tells you the opposite, do you just dismiss it on account of a mere preference?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he doesn't look right or doesn't play the right part that I expect him to play?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you question your own preferences and beliefs?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what position are you in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you the one seeking the way out of suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, if you genuinely think your head is on fire, you would certainly be considering all options that are presented to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be dismissing them because you have... you think you have a privilege to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I don't like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to listen to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, they're not serious enough to practice to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if they were, they would think about things in both ways, regardless of their preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they want a happy monk and positive thoughts, they don't want the dhamma, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just want an engaging, even intoxicating, spiritual dimension to their very kind of household, worldly life.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't really want a change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a place for such people who really don't want dhamma, but they want just kind of Buddhist practice for lay people?
[SPEAKER_01]: Say again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there what?
[SPEAKER_01]: A place for such people.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: In our group, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends what you want your group to be about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want your group to be about something that just caters to your average Buddhist, with whatever preconceived notions of Buddhism they bring in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want to just cater to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you want your group to be about the actual Buddhist teaching?
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, there is no place for those that don't want to follow the actual Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: But maybe they just want these teachings for lay people from Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't teach a different dhamma to lay people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when he was teaching lay people how to look after their wives and be generous and good householder, that was not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was just be a good person so you have a good rebirth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would teach them that because he knew they won't understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your definition of dhamma is things that uproot the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only definition there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because many people have definition like all teachings are dhamma, everything in the world is dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because they haven't read the suttas and haven't read the actual dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've just been hearing second-hand perverted accounts and developed their own notions of who knows what, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some generic religious spirituality, Advaita, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as the Buddha said repeatedly, dhamma only has one taste, which is freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, the ocean has only one taste of salt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether he was teaching it to householders,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or lay... or monks, if it was the dhamma being taught, the principles, the gradual, the virtue, the restraint, the taming of the mind, reflections on the certain... certain topics, there was no exception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there was... as soon as they say that, whether householder or a monk, this is the... this is the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so if people come there and they don't want to do that, then there is no place in that group for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you refuse to let them in.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because they refuse to follow what's required.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's again like you go to a carpentry school and you say, but I don't want to work with the wood.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't like that, but I want to be a carpenter.
[SPEAKER_01]: I still want to be a carpenter, but I don't want to work with wood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that make any sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: By any measure of rational thought, that's insane.
[SPEAKER_01]: Especially when you find out what carpentry entails.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you still want to insist on your own preferences.
[SPEAKER_00]: Should we also include some kind of practice of generosity?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any advice what it might be?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't really know, but you could probably find out, you know, places, communities, things like that, that are in need of help, that can be contributed towards and just organize things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like go and volunteer somewhere as a group, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so many teachers, eh, you are focusing on five precepts, but many teachers, eh, put emphasis on Eightfold Path and other parts of path as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so... Well, those teachers should read the suttas, because, eh, they very clearly say that there is no Eightfold Path without the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you think you're practicing Eightfold Path without being a sotāpanna, you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right view comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the individual factors of the Eightfold Path arise from the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the Sutta cannot be any more clear on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I would, I would advise them to basically read the Suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about Myungdang, right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: What about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is a split for mundane right view and... Well, in a mundane right view, again, there is no ennoblative path in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mundane right view is just the recognition, pretty much recognizing the weight of your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: that you are inseparable from them, that there are things that basically your views will not necessarily comprehend there and then, but that's why you also recognize the possibility of existence of such things, so you don't dismiss them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, the mundane right view is just putujana, who is kind of more acutely and more transparently, more authentically aware of his own situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's described like there is mother, there is father, there is good action, there is bad action, there are results of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even those basic things today, if you were to press people to ask them for it, they would kind of fall into these views of denial or a cover-up and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything would just be boiled down to certain, I don't know, like reductionist psychology, or biology, or physiology, and in reality nothing's real, everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are just forms of denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even most Buddhists today, that follow this commentarial level of teaching, don't even have the mundane right view of recognizing, no, there is good action and bad action.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is good thought and bad thought, and the weight of those things are on me, for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no shared world here that we all partake together.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's me and everybody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how things work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I am the one bound with my own actions, heir to them, and gonna inherit everything implicit, to the extent that I cannot even fathom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just, yeah, I can measure the action and the reaction that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The implications of your actions can span over a course of who knows how many lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't even fathom that at a time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they will keep coming... the results will keep coming back.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact that there are those things that you cannot even comprehend, does not give you the rational basis to dismiss them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like, usually, like, people say, oh, what's the proof that there is rebirth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what's the proof that there isn't one?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have no proof for either, yet the lack of proof for rebirth immediately justifies the vast majority of people in their belief that there is no rebirth, because there is no proof for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, but there is no proof against it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why did you take up that belief?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would say, oh, because you were not transparent and clear enough that you are in a position of not knowing either,
[SPEAKER_01]: And therefore, falling into a belief about one or the other, will basically just be a way of a compromise and a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say that some new people are coming, and should we tell them that there is a river, and then they should contemplate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, again, like, in a broad strokes, but that will not necessarily develop the mundane right view either for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it needs to come internally, a person themselves, internally, need to see that, oh, I'm in a position of not knowing this for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, whatever I choose to believe, will in return reflect on my course of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why when they asked the Buddha the same question, he said basically to recognize that, well, I don't know which one's true, but usually, if I'm dismissing the rebirth, if I'm dismissing the implications of future kind of results of my action, I won't pay much attention to what I do in this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will be careless.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will be acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I kind of lean on the side, poof, there could be a rebirth, which means then there will be implications and results of my actions to the a lot greater degree than I can measure in this life, then you would pay attention to what you do, what you say, what you do to others and how you behave.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it needs to come from your own, as I said, internal recognition and set of values.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just, I'm a Buddhist, I believe in rebirth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, that did not make you any more transparent than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just took another external stance in regard to your position, because you refused to endure that ambiguity of your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say that some new people are coming and they are not keeping precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Should we advise them doing contemplation of anatta, sickness, death?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in broad strokes, you could point out that those are the contemplations that one needs to develop, but then you also need to very specifically tell them that contemplating such things without a basis of virtue and certain degree of being able to contain your own mind will not end well.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has a risk, carries a risk of not ending well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are prodding, you're provoking your mind now towards the contexts and contemplations that naturally no mind wants to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the same time, you're keeping it wild to do whatever he wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you agitate it and then you make it... and then you allow it to behave whichever way he wants as a result of that agitation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not going to be good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it safe... Is it a safe contemplation for people who are not keeping precepts?
[SPEAKER_01]: The value of keeping the precepts and the danger of not keeping them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a safe contemplation for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we can just talk about white-keeping precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and why not keeping them is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, not because somebody will say, oh, you're not a good Buddhist.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because it keeps the very core of your being untamed, wild, whimsical, subject to extreme fluctuations of moods and exposures on the emotional level, and you're going to suffer as a result of it.